john welcome really excited to have you
for those of you guys who are on the
call uh john is the
director of cognitive science now at the
university of toronto
uh freely voted one of the most
life-changing professors at the
university of toronto he's the author of
a book called zombies in western culture
many wonderful you know
primary literature articles in
scientific journals around cognitive
science and meaning
and a series of lectures on youtube
called awakening for the meeting crisis
so
john's work has had just an incredible
influence on my own work
and my conversation with him has been
ongoing and regular
and has meant the world to me so i've
been incredibly pleased
to to learn so much from john and i'm
really really pleased to be able to
share his talk with you guys
so um that's all for me john
take it away thanks rave thanks for that
uh
that wonderful introduction and it's a
pleasure to be here
so um i'm supposed to talk about how
movement and mindfulness work together
to allow or afford
personal transformation and
transcendence so that's what i'm
actually gonna talk about but it's gonna
take me a while to get to
transcendence because it should always
take you a while to get to transcendence
um so what i want to do is i want to
start with
um taking note of two cultural
revolutions
that are happening right now uh the
first is
uh the one that has been called by
several authors
um the mindfulness revolution and then
the second is what i want to call the
embodiment
uh revolution now in both of these
cultural revolutions
we see a synergistic convergence between
an emergence of communities of cultural
practice
and scientific studies so the scientific
academic world is converging on
these topics and that is in
discussion and in relationship with a
cultural emergence of many people
undertaking
uh these relevant practices so let's
take a look at the first one the
mindfulness revolution
let's look for that convergence more
specifically
at the cultural level of course what the
the book the mindfulness revolution was
pointing to was the fact
that we're seeing the widespread growth
of people engaged in
individually and collectively in
mindfulness practices
now that's in convergence with
um increasing psychological cognitive
scientific and neuroscientific study
of mindfulness and it's amazing how
rapid
that has been i started i believe
i i mean i haven't checked all the other
faculty and all the other courses that
have ever been offered at u of t
but i'm i believe i'm the first person
who started teaching academically
about mindfulness at the university of
toronto uh around
1997 and when i started teaching that
i had to sort of teach it like sort of
quietly
and you know everybody's looking at me
like all of a sudden he's going to start
playing beatles music or something crazy
like that
um and so um i had to and if
i wanted to do research on mindfulness
you know
it wasn't so much google then but i
could do an internet search and i could
get
basically all the all the articles and
research being done on mindfulness on
like on
you know i can get it in half an hour
there was nothing
now you there every psychology
department has
multiple offerings in which mindfulness
is being discussed
uh multiple experiments being run if you
google mindfulness as a topic
you're going to get pages and pages and
pages of academic
research so there has been an upsurge
in both the cultural and the scientific
interest in mindfulness
now that scientific study is also it's
not just
sort of a single kind of study there's
multiple domains in which mindfulness is
being studied
it's being studied of course clinically
uh in terms of its capacity for
therapeutic intervention
it's being studied uh cognitively and
that's where my own work on mindfulness
comes
in i published on mindfulness and
what was what mindfulness does
cognitively is it tends to increase
cognitive flexibility
and afford insight please remember that
because we're going to come back to that
connection between mindfulness and
insight later
and of course there's neuroscientific
work showing the neurological changes
that are wrought
uh by mindfulness specifically the way
mindfulness drives
brain plasticity and the rewiring of the
brain
so clearly a huge
upsurge in both cultural practice and
scientific study
of mindfulness i think there's
something very similar going on with
respect to embodiment
now the idea of embodiment of course is
an ancient idea but
the way it's the way i want to use it is
how it has emerged from what is called
4e cognitive science for e cognitive
science
this is the kind of cognitive science
that i i practice at the university of
toronto and it's even the kind of
cognitive psychology
i do and what are the four e's of
for e cognitive science well these are
four claims about
four central features of cognition the
first is that cognition is
embodied there's the embodiment and i'll
come back to that cognition is
inherently embodied
the second that it's inactive en active
inactive
the third is that it's embedded and the
fourth it is that it's extended
and all of these and i'm going to
discuss what these mean in a second but
all of these
are mutually interdefining and
inter-affording
and the core of them of those four is
embodiment i think the rest um in action
embeddedness and extendedness are
actually well forgive the pun extensions
of
the central feature of embodiment so
what's the key idea of embodiment and
how is it going to ultimately relate to
movement
well the key idea here is to see the
brain
and body as an integrated
dynamical system as a self-organizing
system
and to say there's a deep continuity to
to point to this is to point to a
central idea that was developed by
two cognitive scientists francisco
varela and then
my good friend and colleague evan
thompson which is called the deep
continuity hypothesis
this is a hypothesis about there being a
deep continuity
between the biology of the body and the
cognition of the brain
what do i mean by deep continuity well
this is to say
that the principles and
patterns and processes
of biology are
are foundational to cognition in fact
you can see cognitive processes
as deeply similar to and dependent on
those biological principles
and processes so there's a deep
continuity
between the way life is self-organizing
and the way cognition is self-organizing
which means there's going to be a deep
interconnection and interdependence
between the functioning of your brain
and the functioning of your body
so let's take a look at a living thing
let's take a look at a paramecium
well obviously a living thing is a
self-organizing thing
but unlike a tornado a paramecium is
self-organized in order to adaptively
seek out the conditions
of its own existence so tornadoes are
self-organizing things
but they don't seek out the conditions
that will perpetuate their existence
the paramecium is self-organized in such
a way
that it reliably adaptively seeks out
the conditions of that will perpetuate
its own existence that's what makes it a
living thing
now notice right away that the
paramecium
insofar as it's a living thing in so far
is it's what's called an autopoetic
thing
a self-making thing an autopoetic thing
is something that is not just
self-organizing but self-making it
self-organizes in order to continually
maintain and make itself so as soon as i
look at
the principles of autopilesis i see that
the paramecium
is engaged in adaptive seeking
adaptive seeking now that's the core
of actually what cognition is cognition
is the ability to adaptively
seek the conditions that are needed for
existence
in the world see the way your brain is
set up to function
is actually continuous with the way
biological
entities exist as biological entities
so that adaptive seeking what does that
mean go back to the perimysium
the paramecium adaptively seeks out
food but soon as i say that you have to
realize something
food isn't part of the physics of the
world there's no
right there's there's nothing in physics
that defines something as
food food is only a chemical
that is in a particular relationship to
an auto poetic
adaptive seeking thing so the paramecium
in its adaptive seeking is already
making
sense of this chemical
as food or that chemical as
poison see i'm not saying that the
paramecium is conscious or anything
ridiculous like that
what i'm trying to get you to see is the
principles of life
and the principles of cognition are
actually deeply continuous with each
other
so to see to make sense not to see to
make sense
of that chemical as food what's what's
the paramecium doing what the para
museum is is
relating to the world dynamically
coupled to its environment
in such a way that that chemical
literally matters to it it literally
matters to the paramecium it is relevant
and it is literally taken into the
paramecium and that paramecium makes
itself out of it
this is the beginning of the core
feature
of cognition which i call relevance
realization
what you're doing when you're adaptively
seeking your environment and you're
doing it right now
because you're adaptively seeking what
the hell is this guy going to talk about
what's going on here and what you're
trying to do is zero in
on what is going to matter to you and
how is it going to matter to you
how is it going to make a difference to
the way in which you are auto poetically
making your cognition which is
continuous with how you are auto
poetically
making your body brain and body
are one integrated dynamical
system because you are an adaptively
seeking
autopoetic relevance realizing
living thing now what does that mean
that if we now see the brain and body as
an integrated dynamical system
well we have to see that that system
works
by being coupled to the world in what's
called the sensory motor loop
a sensory motor loop and now notice how
movement is
already coming in here we've got
adaptive seeking
as central to cognition and now we're
going to talk about a sensory
motor loop where it means motor movement
so in order to get clear what this new
picture is let's compare it to the old
standard picture
the old standard picture went like this
there's causal stuff out in the world
it makes an impact on me it gets
transduced it gets sent somewhere in
thai till it reaches something like an
inner computer
and then the inner computer does
computation on it
and that's the only place where
cognition is that's where the cognition
is it's in the
computation and then the computation
sends out some signals and then i move
my action
and the only place where the cognition
is is in that very internal spot
the spot of the computation so
there's sensation in cognition and then
action out
that's the old picture and notice how
it's a picture in which the brain
is isolated it's not in a dynamic
coupling to its body
what's the new picture well the new
picture looks like this
the sensory motor loop is suppose i'm
looking at my pencil here
don't understand this as static
passive reception when organisms
are perceiving they are always always
adaptively seeking so when i'm trying to
perceive this object
i will start to move even my eyes will
move
but i will move and as i move i will
change the sensory information
i'm getting and as the sensory
information
changes i change how i move and as i
change how i move
i change how i sense and now i change
how i sense i change
how i move it's not right it's not
perception
computation action it's perception in
action
and action within perception there is a
sensory motor loop that is
constantly evolving in order to
constantly enact
and here's the inaction and help in
order so that i can constantly enact
this adaptive seeking that is at the
core
of cognition now why is the sensory
motor loop need to adapt
well there's always trade-offs
there's always trade-offs i can zoom out
if i want to see all of the pencil
now i move see how i move
i can move in if i want to get more
detail
but they're in a trade-off relationship
and what i will do is i'll move between
them to try and get
an optimal balance between the detail
and the overall picture
but here's the thing there's no final
there's no final place
there's you don't sort of get the
average and sort of stay there in some
sort of canadian fashion
the point is what counts as the optimal
balance for you but in that trade-off
is relative to the information that you
need
in order to meet your auto poetic needs
so sometimes it the
given the context it's more relevant to
me it matters more to me
to get the details sometimes it matters
more to get
the overall shape sometimes it matters
to get the relationship between them
and so the sensory motor loop and
therefore my movement
is always shifting always engaged
and that is not some product of my
cognition
it is the vehicle within my cognition
is actually taking shape that evolving
sensory motor loop that's what it means
to say that cognition is inherently
inactive cognition is that
evolving and i don't mean biologically i
mean dynamically
my evolving fittedness of the sensory
motor loop
to an ongoing changing environment
so notice what we're seeing here we've
already talked about what embodiment is
and inaction is and you're already
seeing how much
there is a deep interpenetration between
embodied movement
and cognition
so let's notice what we've what we've
drawn together here
we've drawn that there is a brain body
coupling
and we've drawn that
perception and action sensory motor
coupling
and we've noted that that loop is
actually coupling the organism to a
dynamically changing environment
so we have three couplings brain body
sensory motor and brain body through
sensory motor
to a world that is dynamically changing
so we actually have cognition is a
meta-coupling
of those three couplings always
happening
together at the same time mutually
affording
and mutually constraining and mutually
informing
each other
what is at the center of this meta
coupling well i keep pointing you to it
it's movement
all of the this meta couple each one of
the individual couplings and the way
they are coupled together
the nexus of that is movement
so what i've tried to argue for first is
this scientific convergence coming out
of 4e cognitive science to the
conclusion
that movement is central to mine
not it's something you happen to do or
you just do
for your survival or you do to get
around no
movement is constitutive to cognition
now that scientific convergence
is well it itself is convergence with
a cultural movement in which we are
seeing the
emergence of embodied you know
communities of practice
that are centered upon embodied movement
um and i think this conference is good
evidence to that fact
so there we go i wish all of science was
like this that i could just gesture
and the empirical evidence would be
ready to hand but here it is
there we go la da okay so
just like in the mindfulness revolution
there was a convergence between
scientific study and cultural practice
also with the embodiment revolution
there is a huge convergence
between scientific study and emerging
the cultural emergence of practice
what's interesting also at this
conference is the fact that these two
revolutions are coming together
they're being drawn together there's a
mindfulness stage and a movement stage
at this conference and more and more
people are pairing these two together
mindful movements and i was very lucky
that
i was taught an ecology of practices and
that included
tai chi chuan as a moving mindfulness
practice
or a mindfulness moving movement
now i want to propose something to you
given this setup i want to make a
proposal to you that i'm going to argue
for
here's the proposal i propose that these
two revolutions are driven
and are driven together what two
revolutions the mindfulness revolution
and the embodiment revolution that these
two
revolutions are individually driven and
are jointly driven together
by the need to recover lost ways of
knowing
lost ways of knowing
and what's going to be a corollary to
that is the reason why we want to
recover them
is because these lost ways of knowing
are central to meaning in life
they're central to meaning in life and
meaning in life is going to be a higher
order version of that sense making
and that adaptive coupling to the world
that is constitutive of your cognitive
agency
so lost ways of knowing that sounds
arcane and it sounds like i'm now going
to
do something telismatic or alchemical or
something that's not what's happening
here
what i want to do is challenge the way
post descartes post newton and kant
and that's all i'm going to do is just
mention their names i'm just going to
drop them in a ridiculously pretentious
fashion
and then continue on um
but since then we have reduced knowing
we to the point where we have identified
it with one kind of knowing
and this is propositional knowing
propositional knowing
is and the vehicle of propositional
knowing is is a proposition of course
and propositional knowing is knowing
that something is the case
and that is the content of a proposition
which is
variously understood as some kind of
fact for example i know that
cats are mammals there we go that's
propositional knowing
and what does propositional knowing
result in it results in beliefs
and if those beliefs have been acquired
by good inferential practice and
evidenced well
then i come to have a theory and then
what's the normative phenomenology
what's my experience
of having good propositional knowledge
by having a good theory
well i get it i get a sense a sense of
conviction of truth
i get a sense of truth that's the way in
which propositions
are that's the way in which i'm being
told by my brain body
that my propositions are picking up on
reality i get a sense of truth
but notice something in order
to do propositions i actually have to
know how to propose
i have to know how to question i have to
know how
to adaptively seek for relevant
information
from the environment my propositional
knowledge is actually dependent on my
knowing how to do many things
this is called procedural knowledge it's
knowing how to do something
and the content of procedural knowing is
not a
proper it's not a fact it's an
interaction with the world a sensory
motor interaction with the world
procedural knowing doesn't result in
belief in theory it results in skills
and when those skills are developed well
so that they
have reliable applicability then
what we have is expertise
and then the phenomenological
normativity of that
is not a sense of truth when i have
expertise
i have a sense of power i'm empowered by
my expertise
i have a sense of power and that's how i
sense realness
in procedural knowledge i don't sense it
as truth i sense it as power
and power is a big way in which we
evaluate if things are
real to us
but notice if i'm going to use or
acquire
a skill i need situational awareness
i i need to be aware of my situation
what skills should i be applying here
should i be applying my swimming skill
right now
i'm a pretty good swimmer should i do it
no it's not and here's the key word it's
not relevant
or appropriate it's not adaptively
fitted to the context that i'm in
i need a situational awareness in order
to know which skills to apply
and which skills to acquire i need to
know what it's like to be here now
in this state of mind
this is called perspectival knowing this
is knowing what it's like to be here now
in this state of mind so you're in a
particular you're
experiencing a particular here now-ness
from a particular state of mind
and what that means is you're doing
salience landscaping salience is how
things stand out
what's happening is things are
constantly shifting and how they're
standing out to you
and what's foregrounded and backgrounded
and what you're doing with all of that
shifting salience landscaping and sizing
up is you're trying to get an
optimal what monopoly called an optimal
grip
on some particular aspect of your
environment so you can interact with it
well
that's what situational awareness is
that's what perspectival knowing
is perspective knowing obviously
the vehicle of that is not a proposition
right it's it's a perspective we talk
about having perspectives
but more accurately you're constantly
enacted and
embedded within a perspective
so perspectival knowing gives me states
of mind that result
and if it's going well i get optimal
grip
what's the sense of realness within
perspectival knowing it's not a sense of
truth
it's not a sense of power i'm working
with dan shapi on this and
with you know with scientists are using
their rovers on mars and people in video
games
virtual reality notice the word virtual
reality
gives us an ongoing experimental arena
in which we can figure out what it is
people are seeking
when they want a sense of realness
within perspectival knowing
and this is the term that people come up
with again and again and again it's a
sense of presence
it's a sense that the world i'm present
in that world and that world
is present to me i'm embedded and this
is the next thing the embedded aspect
of the four e's right i'm embedded in it
i'm perspectively invented
it's present to me and i'm present to it
in that optimal grip
okay
but if i'm gonna have situational
awareness you know what i need for that
i need situations
what's the situation we usually we
use these terms all the time but what's
the situation
what's the way things are situated what
does that mean
well i propose to you that
what we're talking about when we're
talking about the situation is we're
talking about
good coupling remember i've talked about
this meta-coupling
a situation is when the organism
and the environment are coupled together
in the right way
they're situated with respect to each
other
so that they can come to be co-present
to each other
this takes us to the deepest level of
knowing i would argue which i call
participatory knowing
this is not knowing that or knowing how
or knowing what it is like this is
knowing by being
this is knowing by being a particular
kind of agent in a particular kind
of arena and there is only an
agent and an arena if they are
appropriately coupled together how do
they get coupled
together well they get coupled together
and you can
you can examine this at many different
levels of time scales of analysis
at the evolutionary level there are
biological processes a process
called niche construction by which the
environment is shaping organisms and
organisms are shaping the environment
until they mutually shape and it's the
mutual
shaping that causes the coupling that
makes situations
come into existence
you're mutually shaped by the biology at
an evolutionary time scale
but you're also being shaped by
you're being shaped at a historical time
scale by culture
through the use of tools we shape the
environment look around you
to fit you but you also shape you look
at my glasses
look at my clothes to fit my environment
there's a mutual shaping between me and
the environment that is
brought about by culture and of course
there's already something we've talked
about
there's the online mutual shaping
that's going on in the sensory motor
loop watch them all come together
see okay i can
grasp this because there has been a long
process of niche construction
so that i did i might the species but
through speciations
develop this thing the famous opposable
thumb and all that other stuff
so that i can grasp tools and then
culture did this really
interesting thing it shaped matter
and then trained me so that i can drink
from a mug
you can't initially drink from a mug
give one to a five month old
okay so right and then
i have my sensory motor loop that's
giving me
the optimal grip no pun intended or
maybe a pun intended
so that i can actually grasp this mug
and take a drink from it
now where is the grasp ability of this
is it in the mug
no fly can't grasp this the cat can't
grasp this
is it in my hand alone no
it's in a real relationship between the
arena that's a part of the arena and the
agency
a mutual shaping and when that mutual
shapeling when that coupling occurs you
get what are called affordances
affordances there is an affordance of
graspability in that
between that mug and me
so participatory knowing gives you
affordances and when that goes well you
have a sense of belonging
attunement with your environment
perspectival knowing selects from those
affordances
the ones that are particularly relevant
within
your current projects and brings them
into the sensory motor loop and sculpts
and shapes
so that you know which skills to apply
and which skills to acquire and that
gives you your procedural knowing
and then the procedural knowing trains
skills
that you can take into a particular
cultural arena
in which you can use language to make
proposals
that then can be stored as propositions
and the problem with our culture is
we're up here at the abstract level as
saying this is
all what knowing is and everything below
it
is left out of the picture yet
everything below it
especially the deeper you go is where
all the coupling
that makes cognition come into existence
is actually to be found
so if you stay statically passive
holding on to your propositions you will
you are
cut off existentially cut off not
functionally of course
because your body's still doing its best
to do all this work for you
right but you are existentially and
conceptually
culturally cut off from most of the
machinery
of your meaning making and your adaptive
cognitive
agency
think about how you ultimately know your
body
right you know your body through
participatory knowing you don't just
have beliefs about your body
or skills of manipulating it like it's
some sort of cartesian machine
you know your body by being your body
and your body can only be the body it is
by being in the environment to which it
evolved
how do you what about the perspectival
knowing your consciousness how do you
know you're conscious
you know you're conscious by being
conscious
so
how is it that the mindfulness
revolution
and the embodiment revolution are
designed to help us remember these lost
ways of knowing
there's a little bit of um of uh
you know uh fortuitous pun here that the
world the word for mindfulness in
sanskrit is sati which
means to remember to remind and not just
sort of
you know as a fact but a transformative
kind of remembering and reminding
so what is mindfulness well
scientifically that's very difficult so
i'm not going to offer a definition but
i'm going to offer a central feature of
mindfulness
and this is something i publish work on
mindfulness is a meta perspective
awareness i'm going to offer two parts
of it
mindfulness is a meta perspectival
awareness it's your awareness of your
perspectival knowing
your awareness of how you're constantly
doing this salience landscaping
sizing up making things stand out making
things background
you're bringing that that flowing
process of
mentally how you mentally frame yourself
and the environment to each other
you're bringing that into awareness a
metacognitive awareness
john can i interject for one second and
just remind you because i i think it's
it's easy to forget i don't think most
people know
that the greek word of meta means over
oh okay sorry i just
i just think that's that's like it's
it's it
helps so much in understanding a lot of
the things you talk about to recognize
that there's
that it's it's looking from above the
level
normally see things that i'm sorry for
being presumptuous forgive me please
no no i still i just wanted i i thought
it might help people so it's fun
no thank you ray from please interject
if i start to
uh get presumptuous in in in in in any
other way
now what's interesting about this this
this this ability to step back
and look at that's what the meta means
here your own perspectival knowing
as i was recently uh fortunate to belong
to
uh to participate in uh um
a first day workshop and then the
writing of a consensus paper but from
many of the
the central figures who are doing who
are doing work on the psychology
um and the cognitive science and the
neuroscience of wisdom
and one of the things we came to a
convergent conclusion about
is that this meta-perspectival awareness
is central
to wisdom it's central to wisdom and
i'll come back to that
in a sec why would such
meta-perspectival awareness
be central to wisdom and this is of
course part of what these mindfulness
traditions claim
they claim that mindfulness is a way of
cultivating wisdom but how and why
well in order to bring that out i want
to bring out a second aspect
to mindfulness beyond the
meta-perspectival awareness
i think it's also there's an educational
aspect to mindfulness
and this is more controversial not all
mindfulness teachers would agree with me
on this
but i think if mindfulness is not an
educational transformative
uh practice then i think you're
misrepresenting how it
you're misrepresenting it it's original
presentation
uh within things like the buddhist
tradition or the dallas tradition
what's the educational aspect so i want
to give you a quick analogy
to bring out what i mean so
i want to change my perspective and
ultimately and we'll come back to that
my participatory knowing
in that i want to com i want to like
classical music and i don't currently
like classical music
that's not actually true i like
classical music but let's say it was the
case
right so what i can do is i can take a
music appreciation class
and if the thing about this word
appreciation is it's used because it
it connotes three things or maybe
denotes three things at the same time
one is appreciation of the sense i'm
going to come to a deeper understanding
of music
and then secondly i'm going to come to
value music
classical music more and those are going
to interpenetrate each other and
interact each other
and secondly i'm just going to ray i'm
going to go through a transformative
process
right like when we talk about how
something appreciates over time
and so what i would propose to you is
that
mindfulness is meta perspectival
awareness that is designed to
educate an appreciation for perspectival
knowing
so that you come to more deeply
appreciate perspectival knowing why
would you want to
more deeply appreciate understand
value and identify with your
perspectival knowing
well because this ultimately affords
insight this ultimately forwards those
aha moments
because what's going on in an insight
is a pro like you don't you don't do an
insight
you know oh you know what i need an
insight doesn't happen that way
doesn't work that way you also can't
just sort of sit around just like i need
an insight oh well
i'll wait so it's neither active
expression nor static reception
what happens is you have to involve
yourself you have to participate
in a process by which your perspective
will dynamically and dynamical systems
theory is now
used to try and explain insight
in which right your perspectival knowing
which is a dynamical process
will dynamically restructure what you
find salient
or relevant what you background and what
you foreground
that's what's happening in an aha moment
you go oh i didn't realize
this was relevant or i was treating this
as central and it wasn't
so a man lives in the united states this
has nothing to do with current situation
he marries multiple women
in a month he divorces none of them
and none of them die but he doesn't
break any laws
how does he do that
he's a priest he marries many women
to other men now most people get this
after a few minutes of thought
they'll go all right aha
what what was needed how many of you
didn't know that priests could marry
people of course you knew that
you knew that everybody knew that but
why is that why are you initially stuck
because what's salient to you is
another meaning of mary which is to
become someone's spouse
and what you have to do is you have to
shift and you have to let it restructure
itself
so the saliency of the other meaning of
mary
comes into your awareness and you go ah
and you shift your perspective
that's what insight is it is a dynamic
participation in a self-organizing
a self-organizing reconstruction of your
perspectival knowing
and here's the thing mindfulness drives
insight because of it
the way it drives a metacognitive
awareness
and appreciation for perspectival
knowing
and why is that central to wisdom
because
insight is central to wisdom wise people
have the capacity
to adopt a perspective that allows them
insight into
things that we don't see that we don't
understand
the machinery of insight is the same
machinery that you use to overcome
self-deception
think about here's an obvious example
it's not the only example
a lot of your self-deception though a
lot of my self-deception
is because i default to an egocentric
perspective
but with mindfulness i can break out of
that egocentric bias
and that will actually afford me
overcoming a lot of self-deception
that same machinery also enhances my
connectedness
to the world this is why perspectival
knowing and the ability to transform it
is so central to the cultivation of
wisdom and now you see i'm starting to
talk to you what i promised i would talk
to you about
i'm starting to talk to you about
personal transformation and
transcendence
i've already argued that movement is the
nexus
for the couplings the metacoupling that
is at the core of participatory knowing
at the core of your identity and agency
it's at the core of the brain body the
sensory motor
and the brain body world coupling
but here's the thing we have to know
about participatory knowing it can also
go wrong
here's a primary example of this
instance of it not the only one but a
good one
this is based on work of my friend and
colleague mark lewis
who also like me is part of the 4e camp
understanding cognition in terms of
dynamical self-organized
adaptive coupling to the world
here's the thing about mark he uses that
framework to understand emotion
and more importantly for what we're
going to talk about right now addiction
and he talks about addiction in a way
that's different
than how we currently talk about it we
currently talk about
addiction as if it's a disease that we
catch that then compels our
behavior
mark and many others are now arguing
that that model doesn't fit the data
well at all
does not it's a bad analogy
instead mark proposes what he calls a
process that addiction is the result of
what he calls reciprocal narrowing
let's do it very quickly i'm in some
very stressful situation
so i drink some alcohol to try and
alleviate the stress and it does it
really alleviates the anxiety and the
stress and that's wonderful
so i get an immediate sort of short-term
relief
the problem is what that does is it
actually reduces
my cognitive flexibility that adaptive
seeking behavior
it changes my perspective of knowing a
big think about the same room when
you're sober and when you're drunk
okay so it reduces my cognitive
flexibility
what does that mean well that means the
number of problems and the number of
options in my world also decrease that's
scary
that's anxiety producing that's already
gonna
start to limit my cognitive flexibility
because if i scare you
and produce a lot of anxiety your
cognitive flexibility goes down
also this is to put you into what's
called a scarcity mentality
when things are seeming more scarce to
you you also get way more cognitively
rigid
okay so now my cognition narrows a bit
and then the options have gone down and
then that's scary and the anxiety
producing
and my then my cognitive flexibility
narrows even more i get even more rigid
and i probably take more alcohol to try
and deal with that
and then my world is narrowing and then
what happens is my world
and my cognition the arena and the agent
reciprocally narrow until and listen to
the participatory language here
i can't be anything other than i am
and the world can't be any other than it
is there's no
options for me and i am fated and doomed
to do what i do
and that's addiction
but and this is what i said to mark
if reciprocal narrowing is a thing
then so is its opposite reciprocal
opening
that i can enhance my flexibility
and open up the affordance space in my
world
and i can reciprocally open up my the
agent
and arena
and what's powerful about that
is that when you get into reciprocal
opening you experience
love love is not an emotion
oh i'm so tired of that and most of all
it's not a feeling
when you love someone that can make you
angry
sad happy frustrated
love is an existential mode it's a
agent arena way of being love is
reciprocal opening and if i put you into
a situation this has been shown
experimentally
when you start to reciprocally open even
with another person you will start to
experience
love for them
where's the place that i argued is the
nexus
for participatory knowing and therefore
transforming it well it's movement
it's movement
notice how even in the core of religions
when we try and talk about people going
through a huge transformation
we combine perspectival and
participatory
movement we have this term metanoia
here's the meta again by the way it's
translated poorly like converting to a
religion as if you're a chemical
what it what it means is moving
and turning around so that i have a new
perspective
and therefore a new identity is possible
for me
at the core of reciprocal movement at
the core of reciprocal opening
are transformative practices of movement
that integrate participatory and
perspectival
transformation
so
if mindfulness
helps me to remember lost perspectival
knowing
and movement practices helped me to
remember
participatory knowing that putting the
two together would be optimal
in mindful movement and of course that
makes sense because they belong together
perspectival knowing depends on
participatory knowing i've already
argued that
but participatory knowing also comes
into a particular expression within
perspectival knowing
participatory knowing is at the level of
the machinery of the self
perspective knowing is at the level of
the machinery of consciousness
when i bring the two together i have
self-consciousness
self-conscious agency is the core of
personhood
of being a person
anything that causes us to come into a
love of
the machinery that is conducive to
person making i think is central to us
we have evolved to find it intrinsically
rewarding
this comes out in the meaning in life
literature this i study this i'm working
on a
uh another consensus paper on meaning in
life
this isn't the meaning of your life like
some grand destiny that god has written
ahead of time
it's what makes you get up and say my
life is worth all this hell
that i often suffer what does that for
you
and you better have something that does
that for you
what gives you meaning in life
it's an important question
there's there's parts of it part of it
has to do with
good sense making if it's all confusing
man meaning in life goes down
so it's already plugging into all of
that adaptive
sense-making that i've been talking
about but what's really key here
is that the thing that's crucial
is what's called mattering
if i if i sense that i am relevant to
and connected to something beyond my
egocentric perspective that has a value
beyond my egocentric perspective
that is what most significantly makes my
life meaningful
forget all that crap about achieving
your goals
yes purpose matters i'm not going to say
i'm not going to deny that
but you know what it pales in comparison
to mattering
it really does now of course
what's optimal is to integrate the two
together the pursuit of a goal
of increasing your capacity for
mattering
two questions come up one thing is an
observation the other is a question
notice what's happened here we started
with how things literally matter to the
paramecium
and we've gone through because we are
such sophisticated beings
that is now inverted to the problem of
how do i matter to something beyond
myself
how do i belong to something beyond
and what has an intrinsic value above
and beyond your egocentric perspective
persons the making of persons and the
loving of that making of persons
and that's called agape eros is the kind
of love
in which we want to be one with
something by consuming it or being
consumed by it
philia is the love we have when we have
a reciprocal relationship but agape is
the love we have when we matter
to person making when we are causally
coupled to the project of making persons
and making that meaning those meaning
structures that make personhood
possible
we love to be dynamically coupled
to trans-egoic patterns
of patterns and processes
of person making
that's meaning in life
and what what i've tried to show you
throughout
is that we need mindful we need
sustained
wisdom traditions of mindful movement
in order to optimize our chance of
recovering
that capacity for meaning in life
especially within a context
of meaning that is deeply impoverished
so rafe we started about five minutes
later can i go another five minutes or
or what's wrong
go ahead we did want to do a q a um i
think
i think everyone i think everyone's
going to be very happy to stick around
for
a few extra minutes to q a with you so
please go for five more minutes
okay and then we'll do the q a so very
quickly i want to just give you an
example of
mindful movement being connected to
meaning in life and it's another
phenomena i study
um it's the phenomenon of flow named by
chicks at my high
and with uh with leo ferraro and aria
henry and bennett
uh harabena i published an article on
flow the cognitive process as a working
flow
in the oxford handbook of spontaneous
thought now notice notice what's
happening
in flow the flow state and i'm sure you
guys have talked about this
a lot so i'm gonna because of time i'm
gonna be somewhat presumptuous but it'll
also come out what the flow state is
right but know that the flow notice the
flow state is one
that is created by being appropriately
dynamically coupled to the environment
in the flow state your skills already at
the level of procedural knowing by
the way my skills have to be
appropriately
cut you know coupled to the environment
if the if the demands of the environment
are too great i suffer anxiety
if my skills are my skills are too great
i suffer boredom but
when they are appropriately adaptively
coupled
in a dynamical process then i get the
affordance
that set of affordances that we
experience as the flow state
and notice what else is needed for flow
i need
there to be a tight coupling between my
actions and the response of the
environment
tight coupling is right what actually
produces the flow state
and what does that result in well it
results in this wonderful state that
people seek out repeatedly
not because it's pleasurable but it's
deeply rewarding
it's a state of you feel at one with
your environment
a state of deep at one minute notice
that's
a state of sort of optimal participatory
knowing
but the but everything's super salient
to you you feel like there's ongoing
discovery
like i argued in that article there's an
insight cascade this is enhanced
perspectival knowing
mindfulness is afforded by flow training
it's the one form of training that will
reliably increase
your capacity for getting into the flow
state because mindfulness
brings about right mindfulness brings
about
the enhanced kind of cognitive
flexibility that affords insight
and etc but all the stuff i've already
talked about
obviously there's a change in the sense
of presence when you're in the flow
state ever you've seen
everything seems so real everything's
present to you
to you and your present to it but you
know what diminishes in the flow state
but diminishes in the flow state is all
that propositional processing
you stop that nattering nanny of
narrative in your head
how am i doing how am i look
are they noticing that i'm sweating
what's going on do they like me
oh no that falls away
and here's one of the powerful insights
existential insights that come out of
the flow experience
that experience tells you that
egocentric
propositional processing is not the
final locus of your
agency your agency can actually be
enhanced
by mindful movements that take you
beyond it
because in flow what's actually
happening
is an optimization of the agent arena
relationship
and that actually and this is what chick
sent me high and i would argue
it actually develops your
your agency your sense of identity and
your sense of self
in a profound way
and here's what we now know
a quick way to see if people find their
life meaningful is ask them how
frequently they get into the flow state
because if they get into the flow state
they will have enhanced sense of
well-being
and they will have an enhanced sense of
meaning in life
because in the flow state we remember
the perspectival and the participatory
knowing we fall in love again
with the shining aspect of being
and perhaps we then recover
a capacity to deeply remember meaning in
life
in a way that might be relevant to the
meaning crisis that we find ourselves in
but that's another argument for another
day so thank you very much everyone for
your time and attention
can everyone go ahead and unmute
themselves for a second and just give
john a round of applause
john um so
in in we have a question here is there a
place that people can
find uh more of your work your podcast
your research your publications etc
so i mean definitely go to my youtube
video channel
and on there you'll find lots of
conference talks but most importantly
you'll find a lecture series called
awakening from the meeting crisis where
this
a lot of these themes and related themes
are situated in a more
encompassing framework i talk a lot more
about the history
and the structure of this meaning crisis
that i've alluded to
um talk about insight and flow
uh transformative experience etc so
and then you'll also find uh a dialogue
series
a series of um transformative dialogue
that i have with others called voices
with verveiki
rafe has been been on that and um other
people have
i've come on there and where again where
i pursue
these themes and ideas but not in a
monological fashion like i've just done
but in a dialogical uh discussion with
other people because as i've
i indicated in my argument this is all
happening this is not just a scientific
thing that's happening it's a
convergence between
um an emerging scientific field
of investigation and emerging cultural
community you know immune
emerging cultural of communities and
practice and so getting into those
dialogues
is crucial and important so john i've
watched the entire
um series of awakening from the mean
crisis
i have had five dialogues with you i
think publicly and a number
privately um i've read some of your
primary scientific work i've read uh
your
your book um but i think that was one of
the most profound
lectures i've ever seen you give so
thank you so much
i think like there were moments of
insight for me even as someone who's
deeply familiar with your work
and if you look at the the thread here
a lot of people aren't even familiar
with your work they're you know
please lecture for 55 more minutes you
know thank you thank you thank you wow
my mind is blown there was a moment
where you talked about how perspectival
knowing and participating or
uh participatory knowing come together
through
mindfulness practices and movement
practices and when
when when that hit it was like
you know i feel like a window was blown
open for me and
i uh i posted in the
in the thread you know mind blown and
then everyone's like me do
you do me so uh so i just wanted to say
thank you
um what what i would like to do well
rafe i just want to
say thank you for saying that and uh
you're important to me i love you rafe
and so i wanted to
i wanted to give you the best i could oh
man you delivered
absolutely i love you too
so what i want to do guys is i want you
guys to
go into a breakout room for
four minutes where you're gonna process
your insights
with a group of four to five other
people and be able to say
what was the biggest takeaway from you
and what is the one question you really
want to ask john
john if you'll stick around
and um when we come back we'll we'll ask
those questions that are the most
uh that come out of that dialogue we
have with the other people
okay guys so drop your questions in the
chat
um and uh
we'll start with kyle uh kyle's one of
our students uh one of our coaches with
evolved move play and he asks uh
can you give a short answer to solving
the meaning crisis
um that's a difficult question
so the short answer
is we need
[Music]
communities and ecologies of practices
and some of those practices have to be
higher order practices
for for coordinating the ecology of
practices
that will help people reliably cultivate
wisdom so that they can overcome
perennial problems
of self-deception and disconnection
and afford enhanced connectivity and
that that has to be situated
within i would argue a cognitive
scientific worldview
that properly homes that community
of wisdom practices
boom that's good um andrew says
return of the source is a good place to
start
that's our big event which we hope to
have john out for one of these years
um given that uh the medic my blood
pressure medication has been working
quite a bit better
that's more likely now beautiful just
got to deal with this covert thing
brandon asks if you can expand on or
elaborate
uh on affordances a little bit yeah so
affordances was originally a notion
drawn
from gibson um my colleague jordan
peterson has made use of the notion
uh i don't think without properly giving
credit to gibson so
oh no he definitely talks about gibson i
can say that for sure okay
good good i haven't seen him do it in
some of the lectures that i've attended
at conferences but
i'll take your word for it uh uh rafe
and so uh affordances is it's the idea
that and this is what that perception
cognition
work in terms of these real relations so
this is the this is what we have to get
we have to stop thinking that reality
listen to the word reality res the thing
latin
we have to stop thinking of reality as
in things and that the relations between
them are just sort of mental acts we
perform
uh that's called nominalism and what
we're now coming to see
and this is even in sort of in science
what's called structural realism
we're coming to see is that no the
relations
are actually as real or if not more real
than the things related
um and you know you can see this both at
the high level macroscopic and
relativity which is ultimately
a real relational theory and low-level
quantum mechanics and etcetera
okay so given that what we have to
understand is that
there is here's my example there is a
real relation
between this thing and my hand
that makes it graspable it's not a
property of this thing
or this thing but it is a property of
the real relation between them
this floor is walkable by me
right these clothes are wearable by me
and there's clothes that are not
wearable by me especially if i
don't lose some more weight okay
so the idea of an affordance
is that there are real relations and i
keep
emphasis there are real relations they
they are just as real as the things
related
and those real relations are where
important properties
that are at the center of our ability to
interact successfully with the
environment
are to be found i can interact with this
because it's graspable
the graspable is not in my hand or in
the cup but in the real relationship
between them
i hope that answered the question
well uh we'll uh we'll see we'll see
what he says uh if he feels
a successful answer but let's move to
this question um
i'm trying to monitor the chat so i uh
so i'm hoping i'm tuning in all the way
but
um i i think it's it's such a deep
concept affordances and it
it's a little bit different than we've
thought than the way that a lot of
people think but it
it's so important once you grasp it to
understand
what we're doing um so vicky asks
um when we know that the main practices
in society are wrong
like look at the use of plastic
packaging how do we live in a society
that there's so much stuff that is
uh that's that's she says bad or wrong
um with regards to meaning yeah
that that's i mean that takes me into uh
a couple of things there's two aspects
of that
this is a deep question one is um around
a
thing called modal confusion um
and our cultural environment especially
the packaging and promotion
and commodifying of things tends to push
modal confusion what's modal confusion
uh the idea is remember i talked about
that love is an existential mode
and that there's the agent arena
relationship that's an existential mode
and so we have two existential modes
according to eric from we have one
that's organized around
having needs these are needs that are
met by controlling and consuming i need
to have water
and so what do i want to do well i i
want to relate to things in terms of
their categorical identity
that water there or that water there and
if i can't get that water that water is
just as good as long as they're both
equally free from disease etc so i
relate to things
in terms of their categorical identity
and how i can there by manipulate them
in order to satisfy my having needs and
there's nothing wrong with that if you
don't do that you're dead
the paramecium doesn't get its food it's
dead but you're not just a paramecium
you go the other way remember
and so you have what are called being
needs these are the needs that are met
not by having something and consuming it
or controlling it but by entering into
right relationship with it
so that you become something so that you
go through a perspective and
participatory
transformation i need to become mature
in order to become mature i have to
enter into right relationships with
other people
and with myself and with the world
i need to be in love
now what happens for people and this is
especially the case in our culture
is we tend to try and satisfy our being
needs within the having mode
so in order to be mature i have a car
in order to be in love i have sex
or in order to be a friend i have lots
of likes
on social media and so that is
and and the reason why that's prevalent
in our culture is it
the more of your needs i can get you to
try and approach from the having mode
the more i can sell you stuff
and manipulate you and get you to adopt
ideas and so modal confusion is a
profound source
of frustration in the project of meaning
in life
and so that's the sort of socioeconomic
pollution the way things can be bad for
us in our environment
and that's where waking up
satie remembering the being regularly
and reliably practicing
the being mode and being able to
engender i'm trying to you know because
you can't make it but
to engender the participatory
realization of agape
is one of the central ways of responding
to that
on the other side on the more sort of
physical and biological side and
and then but it's not separate from the
socio-cultural this is
you know this is a more radical aspect
of my thinking i suppose
i'm not sort of political i call myself
metapolitical
i talk about stealing the culture and
what i mean by that
and and i think you guys exemplify what
i'm talking about the model i have for
that
i don't want the french revolution i
want the axial revolution
right and what do i i want what happened
right
in think about and i'm not advocating
for
christianity but think about what
christianity does you have small
communities of practice
in which people are remembering the
being mode and practicing agape
and moving and singing and doing all
this kind of stuff together
and they're not trying to topple the
state because they can't it's too
powerful it's too overwhelming
but what do they do they build from the
bottom up a new culture a new way of
seeing and being
and it permeates up and then the whole
civilization
is eventually transformed they stole the
culture
from the roman empire and i think what's
happening now
has that potential and i think we need
to do that
right now and so i think
what you guys are doing in these
communities are addressing both of those
you're meeting together and regularly
and reliably remembering the being mode
and entering into agape and then you're
also
sowing the seeds for a new culture what
what stephen batcher calls a culture of
awakening
that can steal the culture from the
people who have rendered it so
toxic for human life
it's beautiful john i i wanted to to
just amplify and pick up on a couple of
themes in that
um there was a question in the group
that i had about
how how do you how do you
be be in this when other people
aren't seeing it yet and that played
into a question that we had had
uh in the previous conversation with
sebastian fukan about
the role you know the difficulty of
feeling like you have this beautiful
thing
and that people could be transformed by
it but people don't see it or are afraid
or can't do it yet and that you have to
have the patience
to know that if you keep doing the thing
that there will be people who find
inspiration from it and it may not be
here in this moment
but just keep keep stealing the culture
and and i i give the example of of agape
right and um this is something that i
that i learned from you but there's
those three words right eros is the word
of
you we the the love that wants to
consume
philly is the love secret reciprocation
and agape is the love that
that helps something come into being
that is given
before it is earned and and you know
i'm not committed to the metaphysics or
the are supernatural of
of of uh of christianity any more than
you are
um but i think when when jesus says love
thy neighbor and he uses that term
that's that's the answer to this
question right like
you have to see the world around you and
all those people who are doing things
that might not be toxic
as people who have that potential to
bring good into being
yeah you can behave from that place
that's ultimately what steals the
culture
would you agree with that i would and i
mean you're picking up on saint paul
also um you know what he said be in the
world but not of the world
again like you i'm not advocating
christianity i'm not committed to its
metaphysics or it's
it's supernatural um claims but the idea
that we can be in the world
um but not being of the world which is
and this in this in this converges with
stoicism
that we ultimately
have a lot more i mean epictetus begins
his manual for living
notice the title of the work the great
epithelia
the great uh philosopher he said you
know the core of wisdom is to
be able to discern what's in your
control and what's not in your control
and what we do is we regularly think and
try to have more of the world in our
control
and not pay very much attention to the
meaning making machinery
when when when what is actually the case
is that the invert the inverse is true
we actually have a lot more control over
the meaning making machinery
and a lot less control over the world
than we'd like to believe that we have
and to live that way is to live in the
world but not of the world
right so if i if i am more and more
what what's centered in
the meaning making machinery which is
what we're talking about here
and that doesn't mean sitting passively
it means doing all the stuff we're
talking about here
right then i can be in the world
but i don't have to be overwhelmed
by it because ultimately
most of my distress is not
caused by the world but by the meaning
of events in the world now some of it's
caused
literally by the world object hits me in
the head i'm dead
but a lot of my distress is actually
caused
by the meaning of events as opposed to
the events themselves
so i can live in the world of events but
i don't have to be of that world
was the epic tetus who said um
you cannot control what happens to you
you can only control how you respond
basically yes that's exactly it
beautiful
um slightly different tech
uh i feel like we could go on quite a
quite a long ways with that it's it's
such a
deep a deep line of conversation if
people just can i say one more thing
about it
i want to be clear that i want i want
people to put those two things together
right i don't i don't want them to
forget the first point in the second
point
right so i'm not i'm not i mean one
mistake you can get into with what the
sort of
that aspect of christianity and stoicism
is you can get into sort of a
contentedness with the status quo
right um and that's not i'm not
advocating that i want to steal the
culture
but what i'm saying is one of the ways
of stealing the culture is to not
confuse
the events with the meaning that the
culture is trying to assign to those
events
for some reason what pops into my head
right there is the that paradoxical
thing in the uh
and in the daodejing the sage does
nothing but nothing is left undone
yes exactly yeah that's exactly it
so charles asks what do you think is a
better approach
a top-down approach where you choose an
ecology of practices and then begin them
or just start doing things and
organically craft your own practice
so i'm going to give you a frustrating
answer charles but it's the answer that
comes out of everything i i've been
arguing
you need to be doing both simultaneously
um
just like when you're reading you need
to be looking at the whole word
to disambiguate the letters and you need
to be looking reading the letters in
order to be able to figure out what the
whole word is
and that's what happens in reading
you're constantly moving top down and
bottom up at the same time
in fact you're doing it now in fact
you're doing it all the time
and so i would recommend and i know
you're going to say well that's so hard
that's
yeah it is but if you're asking me in
terms of speaking as a cognitive
scientist what's the optimal way of
trying to get one going
i think you need to do both you need to
be doing
uh some top-down organization so
what are some of the top-down
organizational features you should be
looking for
in an ecology of practice you should be
looking for relationships of
complementarity
how various practices have complementary
sets of strengths and weaknesses
and you should seek to put them in into
relationship with each other
so that they self-correct each other uh
so
uh you know meditation tends to take you
inward
uh contemplation takes to take tends to
take you outward and you need to have
both of them because they act as checks
and balances on yourself
suited practice needs to be put into a
complementary relationship with moving
practice
so you need relationships of
complementarity you also need
you need relationships of linking you
need practices that move you between the
kinds of knowing
the way like the way chanting takes you
from propositional
into perspectival and participatory or
lectio divina does the same thing
and you also need uh you need principles
of layering
various practices layer on top of each
other if you do enough mata practice
and enough the pasta practice you can
then move into what's called a prajna
practice
a form of of mindfulness that moves
both in both directions at the same time
and realizes what's called
non-duality so there are top-down
principles for how you want to create
your ecology of practice but you also
need to do an auto bottom-up
participatory observation because you
aren't
i you we are not aware of most of the
relevance realization machinery and we
don't know what's going to
you know be particularly i don't mean
with your sort of initial impressions
because
our initial impressions are usually off
i mean really deep participatory
observation because you need to find
those practices that gel
with your own idiosyncratic background
and development
so you need both the top down principles
of organization
but you need the bottom-up participation
in many different things
it's interesting john because one of the
things that's come up in our
conversation
is how in many ways uh
what evolved move play has it evolved
into from kind of the seed of parkour
and time in nature
uh is so reflective of the top down
vision of what an ecology of practices
can be that you're proposing
right i agree with that wholeheartedly i
think i mean
i often use your community practice
as as an exemplary case of the kind of
thing i'm talking about when i'm talking
about an ecology of practices
that is directed i think in a powerful
way
to help people awaken from the meeting
crisis
thank you um so there's a lot of
questions about the flow state
right so what i i'm going to throw i'm
going to throw a few at you and see
what you feel like you want to because
it's time's running light and i i just
want to see you know it's all about flow
so i want to see what what about flow
you're most
interested in sharing so one asks what
is the role of intuition and flow
another yep
what is the role of introspection to
find meaning after flow since you're not
aware of it necessarily within it
um and what about
the the aspect of being kind of and
another question has to do with the
aspect of
of being in an individual flow state and
how that
impacts the community how that can be
integrated in the community so i don't
know if you can weave these together
into an answer that's very satisfying
but
i can leave the first and the third and
i'll try and come back
maybe therefore to the second after
doing the first and the third
okay so i talk a lot uh leo and erin and
i talk a lot about intuition
in the article on flow in fact we
propose that
the mechanisms of flow are an insight
cascade
it's kind of like you're having a bunch
of aha moments that are chaining each
other together
and affording each other but also um
you're getting enhanced intuition
now in order to answer that i have to
quickly talk about what intuition is
um because we need to take it out of the
clutches uh well the
the decaying clutches of decadent
romantics because intuition isn't a
magical power you have
um that will you you should not try to
deify or demonize any one of your
faculties
none of them is safe from self-deceptive
self-destructive behavior
um what is intuition well
um intuition is the result of what's
called implicit learning
so implicit learning is the fact that
you can pick up
on complex even dynamically complex
patterns
in your environment uh and what you're
doing is largely bypassing working
memory
you're largely bypassing sort of an
explicit awareness of
picking up on these patterns and when
that goes well you have intuition and
when it goes badly
you call it prejudice or bias
so you have to be careful about leaping
to conclusions about
how this process is always good it's not
it can it can go bad
which means it needs to be properly
educated it needs to be properly
educated now we can
we know how to experimentally study
implicit learning we've been doing it
for quite a long time
um it's really interesting by the way um
sort of concrete examples of this if
you've got if you ask people to make a
decision um
and there's only a couple of relevant
variables then they should think about
it very explicitly
but if you ask them to make a decision
that involves a whole bunch of
dynamically integrated
um variables their intuitive judgment
will often work
better except when it goes wrong and
then it goes disastrously wrong
so you can pick up on complex patterns
and that gives you what happens in
intuition
you often know things without knowing
or remembering how you came to know them
that's what intuition is and you do you
do that you do this all the time
and and you do it often only in even a
semi-conscious manner
you will adjust how far you stand from
somebody given their status
your status and the social context with
where
that you're in how close you stand to
them
just move you just do that and you'll
know and you won't be aware of this
until you go to another culture
and you'll be standing the inappropriate
distance from people
but what you've done is you've picked up
on that complex set of variables
through implicit learning and that's
giving you your intuition now the
problem as i said with intuition is it
can go disastrous
disastrously wrong it can pick up on
what it does is it picks up on all kinds
of patterns
and so it doesn't distinguish and here's
the crucial
this is where the power and peril of
intuition comes to a crux
it doesn't distinguish between
correlational patterns and causal
patterns
you know what correlational patterns are
things are often correlated but there
isn't any causal relationship
between them right so
you know i was brought up a
fundamentalist christian and they would
often say you know they took prayer to
the schools and crime went up it didn't
by the way but that's
that's irrelevant because here's another
correlation
greenhouse gas emissions have gone up as
caribbean piracy has gone down
so what does that mean we should bring
back caribbean piracy
that will deal with the the climate
change of course that's ridiculous
because that's a correlational pattern
it's not a causal pattern and there are
way more correlational patterns than
causal patterns
that is why we do science
science is the project of trying to
distinguish the causal patterns
from all the correlational patterns and
when you just do intuition
you pick up on all of them without any
good discernment
so what you want to do is you want to
try and
set up the condition conditions for
implicit learning
so they're like the conditions of
science
what are those conditions well what i
want is i want conditions where i'm
getting clear feedback
in science i need clear measurement in
science there is a
tightly coupled relationship between the
what's called the independent variable
and the dependent variable i do
something in experiment
and there's a result and error matters
failure matters my hypothesis can be
falsified by my experiment
what i want to do is i want to go into
situations where i'm
implicitly learning but i'm getting
clear feedback
it's tightly coupled and error matters
you know what those are the conditions
for
flow
flow is also a place not only where
you're getting
training in the cognitive flexibility
and you're getting all kinds of insight
you're also getting enhanced implicit
learning you're intuitively picking up
on the causal patterns
now flow can be hijacked like everything
else that's adapted it could be hijacked
by video games
but flow evolved why you find flow so
rewarding
is because it's enhancing your insight
capacity and it's enhancing your
capacity
for intuition good implicit learning
implicit learning that is tending to
zero in on the causal patterns
rather than the correlational patterns
and here's the thing they mutually
afford each other
because another thing that your implicit
learning doesn't do is
it only attaches to actual patterns it
doesn't explore possible new ones
but if you attach insight to good
intuition
the implicit learning is also exploring
the new possibilities created by the
insight
so if you take the insight cascade of
flow
and the good intuition of flow and put
them together you get this
optimal state which is why flow is a
state of optimal experience and optimal
performance
that is the central role of intuition
within flow
what does that have to do with
individual and collective
so i am engaged in a long project of
participatory observation
and i'm i'm editing and writing for an
anthology a book and doing
a work and you know cognitive science
trying to understand
how we can get group flow states uh
within
dialogue process that i call dialogos
and discourse
because i think that is the only way
remember i said there were four things
about the
cognitive the carbon science embodiment
enacted
embedded embedded i didn't talk about
the last one extended but i will right
now
extended is the idea that most of our
problem solving
most of our cognition is done and is
done well
when we are networked together with
other people
that way before the internet networked
commute computers together
to give us this emergent power of the
internet culture
network brains together through language
and gesture
to give us this enhanced capacity for
problem solving most of our problem
solving is done in concert with other
people
this is not to say we should not engage
in individual responsibility
please that doesn't follow from what i'm
saying but
what i think we need to do is to tap
into the collective intelligence that is
available
in that networking what's called
distributed cognition extended cognition
and learn how to get the flow state
going there so we can
ramp that collective intelligence up
into collective wisdom
because we need the collective wisdom so
that we have
a home and a school that gives us a
place where we can
get what we need in terms of
information and transformation for how
we curate
and cultivate ecologies and practices so
i think we need to really learn how to
bring flow
into distributed cognition and and
direct it towards the cultivation of
wisdom
and so that's the answer to the first
and the third
i'm trying to remember what the second
one was right what was the second one
uh that one that was i think ben's
question
uh so where was it
um the role so
once you enter the flow state you don't
worry about this retrospective
yes once all that is said and done
defined meaning wouldn't there also need
to be a period of introspection as a
retrospective afterwards
yeah i wouldn't say so much
introspection i would say a moment of
reflection and so i think i i
i'm sorry if i misled you ben i i do not
think that the flow state is
the sole or exclusive practice we should
be engaging in
in order to respond to the meaning
crisis i was using that as a particular
as an exam as a particularly exemplary
case i think we need to be doing lots of
other practices other other wisdom
conducive practices
um and some of those are communal and
some of them are extended across time
and some of those involve training
reflective training reflection
and adjust the way you're talking about
so there are various kinds of journaling
practices there are various kinds of
biological practices with others
that help you get into and help to
enhance this reflective capacity
so that you can situate those moments of
enhanced connectivity that happen
to you within a more expansive framework
beautiful um
let's see so there were some questions
about intuition i i
i would like to just put a pin in that
really quickly because i think it's
something that that's such a profound
insight
and that people really need to digest
you said that that
intuition can go wrong yes and i think
that
that there is there's part of our
culture that that really
has fallen in love with intuition in
some sense because we've seen the
limitations of reason as a system
yes um and so perhaps the answer to if
it's not reason then it's intuition but
actually both share the same dangers and
what people
seem to realize is that that the dark
side of intuition
is stereotypes and yes yes
and those are actually the same system
in the brain and i and
people who talk about implicit bias will
say that intuition is everything
and those two things are are are inca
commensurate so i just wanted to really
put a pin in that for people because i
think it
it's very powerful and it's really at
the heart of your inside of
how we have to build these systems that
allow us to
reciprocally use reason and intuition
such that they work better over time
that's what i meant about those
relationships of complementarity between
practices
and those relationships of linking
and layering all of that needs to be
done to get that massive
kind of recursive self-correction so
that we can optimize the whole
because it's only in the optimization of
the whole of our cognitive processes
the full the fully the full brain fully
embodied fully embedded
that we have our best shot at overcoming
self-deception
and disconnection
um so we're
we're about 40 minutes over uh how long
this talk was scheduled for but
i mean it's just amazing to see this uh
the the enthusiasm that everyone has for
this and and
the power of this so thank you guys so
much um i i wanted to point you guys to
a couple things one if you want to be
able to see this again if you want to go
through this information it's very dense
we do have 24 hour for free replay of
this you can come back and watch it
again tomorrow
but also you can upgrade to the all
access pass and you can come back and
watch this multiple times
in addition to that um john has
meditation education programming
on his channel you can go and do
meditation with him every week
you have uh how often do you do question
answers on your channel
um john the we do
i do the the meditation live stream
every day and we do a q a about that the
meditation contemplation
um but all of those have been recorded
and you can
watch through them at your leisure i
think we've got like 80 or so now up
there and then a general q a is every
third friday of the month at 3 p.m
eastern time so tomorrow
july 17th at 3 p.m on youtube i'll be
there and doing general q a
beautiful so yeah so there is there's
all those resources for you guys um and
then
there are questions about uh for people
who are interested in understanding more
about intuition i mentioned daniel
kahneman's book uh
thinking fast and slow hogarth's book
educating intuition i think is a really
good book
okay i mentioned that i couldn't
remember the author so those are a
couple and uh
i i know p folks would be incredibly
appreciative if you create a little
reference list for us
after this conversation is that possible
sure sure that's that's very possible
beautiful so i think that um
i i think that that's going to be i i
think we've we've gone through most of
the questions i'm sure more could be
generated
but i do want to be respectful of your
time and uh
give something because
me too um so yeah so i guess um
well thank you i guess that's that's
that's what i need to say is thank you
so much that was
incredible thank you for everyone who
was in the group who brought your
enthusiasm
and uh you know
the engagement was just through the roof
here you know they're saying thank you
so much john this has been extraordinary
says tegan
um addie yeah a thousand thank yous to
john from
uh from uh orlando um
this is timeless from chris odell
amazingly insightful from sally
uh yeah i i think
the the response of the audience speaks
to itself and i i feel
immensely honored to have been able to
to to
to introduce many of these people to
your work so uh thank you guys
well thank you so much ray well you know
uh
i i believe deeply in what you're doing
and i think this conference well i said
i think this is
part of where you know we are building
the
capacity to steal the culture so it
matters deeply to me and i was honored
being here
and i deeply appreciate uh such a
receptive
and and welcoming audience and i also
appreciate
uh the quality and the candor of the
questions that were asked of me so thank
you very much for all of that
beautiful so yeah everyone uh
just there's a stream of of of uh of
appreciation over here
which is really wonderful to see so we
have um paul check coming up next paul
check
is kind of the one of the most
profound thinkers for a long time around
how we bring well-being
in a much bigger sense into our thinking
around health and fitness
so he's going to be talking about uh um
well-being through movement so that's at
three
so we've got an hour and 15 minutes and
then after that
um we'll have ryan hurst from gmb he's
gonna be talking about the power of
exploration he's gonna be getting you
guys actually moving
um and and exploring different movement
patterns i believe so
got some really exciting things coming
up um
john is incredibly generous with his
time and
you know i know you all answer questions
i folks send them to you as well there's
uh there's also the awakening from the
median crisis group
on facebook which is run by some friends
of mine that people can check out
there's also an awakening from the
meaning crisis discord server that
you can get involved with uh where they
have lots of groups discussing all of
this work
really vibrant and vital community i
also appear there
um bi-weekly like every two weeks
um on monday 6 p.m eastern time and do a
general q a
there as well yeah and they brought me
on to uh
things they brought on a bunch of other
people who i really respect who have
been deeply influenced by john's work
so there's just a yeah we're gonna
andrew says we need links to all these
places on the speaker stage so we're
gonna put together a big resource
package for you guys because obviously
the
the level of engagement with this is
through the roof
and um yeah i i think i could go on it's
just
it's just been so good but uh but all
things must come to an end
and at least for the moment and we'll
we'll be doing more stuff like this
together
well for sure for sure thank you so much
again ray for
inviting me and thank you one and all
it's been a great pleasure thank you
very much
adios guys